# Alberto Fachechi



http://albertofachechi.github.io

# **Activity and research interests**

My research activity is placed in the wide discipline of statistical mechanics methods for complex systems analysis, in particular concerning **spin-glass theory** and its application to modern **Artificial Intelligence** and **Machine Learning**. The core research interest consists in the development of rigorous mathematical techniques, involving in particular Guerra's interpolating schemes, non-linear PDE theory, probability and statistics and random matrix theory. My research interests also cover the application of statistical inference tools to real-world (in particular, biological) problems.

#### **Positions**

• Researcher (RTD-A).

Department of Mathematics G. Castelnuovo, Sapienza University of Rome.

**2021 – 2023** • **Post-doc researcher.** 

Department of Mathematics G. Castelnuovo, Sapienza University of Rome.

**2020 – 2021** • **Post-doc researcher.** 

Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, Unisalento.

2019 – 2020 • **Research fellow.** 

Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, Unisalento.

#### **Education**

2016 – 2019 • Ph.D. in Physics and Nanosciences.

Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, Unisalento.

Thesis title: Statistical mechanics for Artificial Intelligence: Learning, Retrieving, Unlearning and Sleeping.

• M.Sc. in Theoretical Physics of Fundamental Interactions.

Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, Unisalento.

Thesis title: Higher-spin Lifshitz theories and integrable systems.

2009-2013 • B.Sc. in Physics.

Department of Mathematics and Physics E. De Giorgi, Unisalento.

Thesis title: *Integrability in AdS/CFT*.

#### **Communities**

2016-2017

• FAIR foundation (Future Artificial Intelligence Research).

Partecipation as researcher in the group of Artificial Intelligence at Department of Mathematics, Sapienza University of Rome.

 National Group for Mathematical Physics (GNFM-INdAM), section of mechanics for discrete systems.

> GATIS (GAuge Theory as an Integrable System), section of Bologna, National Institute for Nuclear Physics (INFN).

• National Institute for Nuclear Physics (INFN), section of Lecce.

# **Teaching**

2023-2024

- Co-lecturer for the course of Calculus and Biostatistics for the academic year 2023-2024 (together with Prof. Elena Agliari), Department of Biology and Biotechnologies, Sapienza University of Rome.
- Teaching assistant for the course of Elements of Probability and Statistics for Data Science for the year 2023-2024 (resp. Prof. Alessandra Faggionato), Department of Mathematics, Sapienza University of Rome.
- Lecturer for the course of **Statistical learning and neural networks: a short introduction to Artificial Intelligence** for the academic year 2023-2024 in the context of the "Excellence Program", Department of Mathematics, Sapienza University of Rome.

2021-2022

• Co-lecturer for the course of **Mathematics** for the academic year 2021-2022 (resp. Prof. Raffaela Capitanelli), Department of Architecture, Sapienza University of Rome.

2020-2021

Supervisor for the course of Mathematics for Economy and Finance for the academic years 2019-2020 and 2020-2021 (resp. Prof. Luca Anzilli), Department of Economy, Unisalento.

# **Supervising**

- Supervisor for the ACU course essay by Yuriy Dosyak with title *Bayesian approach to supervised learning: mathematical approaches to automatic learning,* Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome (IT).
  - Co-supervisor (together with Prof. Elena Agliari) for the PhD thesis in Mathematics by Domenico Luongo with title *A Random Matrix Theory Perspective on Hebbian-Like Neural Networks*, Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome (IT).
- Supervisor for the M.Sc. thesis in Mathematics by Benedetta Giovannelli with title Statistical
  mechanics of spin-glasses for Artificial Intelligence and Machine, Sapienza Università di Roma,
  Rome (IT).

2022-2023

- Co-supervisor (together with Prof. Elena Agliari) for the PhD thesis in Mathematics by Chiara Marullo with title *Rigorous techniques for Statistical Mechanics of Machine Retrieval*, Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome (IT).
- Co-supervisor (together with Prof. Elena Agliari) for the M.Sc. thesis in Mathematics by Donatella Genovese with title *Effective training strategies for Restricted Boltzmann Machines*, Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome (IT).
- Co-supervisor (together with Prof. Elena Agliari) for the M.Sc. thesis in Mathematics by Matteo Notarnicola with title On the thermodynamic limit of bipartite spin glasses, Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome (IT).

• Co-supervisor (together with Prof. Elena Agliari) for the M.Sc. thesis in Applied Mathematics by Chiara Marullo with title *Neural network beyond the Hebbian paradigm*, Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome (IT).

# **Funded projects**

- PI for the project **Rigorous statistical mechanics for Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning** in the context of Progetto Giovani 2023 funded by National Group of Mathematical Physics (GNFM).
- PI for the project **Replica Symmetry Breaking in modern Artificial Intelligence** in the context of Progetto Avvio alla ricerca 2022 funded by Sapienza University of Rome.

# Funded projects (continued)

- Partecipant to the project Large scale multicomponent random systems (ref. Prof. Vittoria Silvestri) funded by Sapienza University of Rome (Progetto di Ricerca Medio).
- Partecipant to the project **Rigorous approaches to Deep Learning** (ref. Prof. Elena Agliari) in the context of Progetto Giovani 2018 funded by National Group of Mathematical Physics (GNFM).

## Other roles

2024-Today

• **Responsible for communication** for the FAIR foundation, Spoke 5 (WP5.5) for the organization of scientific and dissemination events.

2024

• **Organizer** of the VI Scientific Meeting for the FAIR foundation.

2023-Today

 Member of the Department Assembly, Department of Mathematics, Sapienza University of Rome.

2022

• **Project reviewer** for the Isreal Science Foundation.

2018-Today

• **Review editor** for Frontiers in Physics, section of Social Physics.

2017-Today

 Referee for several high-impact journals, in particular Nature Scientific Reports; Journal of Mathematical Physics; Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical; Neural Computation; Journal of Physics: Complexity; Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications; Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment; Machine Learning: Science and Technology.

## Recognitions

• Outstanding reviewer for IOP publishing for my contributions to the *Journal of Physics: Complexity*.

• **Special mention** for my PhD thesis from the selection board of Fubini Prize 2021 (INFN).

2020 • Truster reviewer for IOP Publishing.

# Summary of scientific production

Total number of publications	27
Total number of citations <sup>1</sup>	388
Total $h$ -index <sup>1</sup>	10
Total $i10$ -index <sup>1</sup>	10

# Full list of publications

#### **Journal Articles**

- [1] E. Agliari, F. Alemanno, M. Aquaro, and **A. Fachechi**, "Regularization, early-stopping and dreaming: A hopfield-like setup to address generalization and overfitting," *Neural Networks*, vol. 177, p. 106 389, 2024.
- [2] E. Agliari, **A. Fachechi**, and D. Luongo, "A spectral approach to hebbian-like neural networks," *Applied Mathematics and Computation*, vol. 474, p. 128 689, 2024.
- [3] **A. Fachechi**, E. Agliari, M. Aquaro, A. Coolen, and M. Mulder, "Fundamental operating regimes, hyper-parameter fine-tuning and glassiness: Towards an interpretable replica-theory for trained restricted boltzmann machines," *arXiv preprint arXiv:2406.09924*, 2024.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Source: GoogleScholar.

- [4] E. Agliari, M. Aquaro, A. Barra, **A. Fachechi**, and C. Marullo, "From Pavlov conditioning to Hebb learning," *Neural Computation*, vol. 35, no. 5, pp. 930–957, 2023.
- F. Alemanno, M. Cavo, D. Delle Cave, et al., "Quantifying heterogeneity to drug response in cancer–stroma kinetics," *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*, vol. 120, no. 11, e2122352120, 2023.
- [6] E. Agliari, A. Fachechi, and C. Marullo, "Nonlinear PDEs approach to statistical mechanics of dense associative memories," *Journal of Mathematical Physics*, vol. 63, no. 10, 2022.
- [7] A. Fachechi, A. Barra, E. Agliari, and F. Alemanno, "Outperforming RBM feature-extraction capabilities by "dreaming" mechanism," *IEEE transactions on neural networks and learning systems*, vol. 35, no. 1, pp. 1172–1181, 2022.
- [8] E. Agliari, L. Albanese, F. Alemanno, and **A. Fachechi**, "A transport equation approach for deep neural networks with quenched random weights," *Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical*, vol. 54, no. 50, p. 505 004, 2021.
- [9] **A. Fachechi**, "PDE/statistical mechanics duality: Relation between Guerra's interpolated p-spin ferromagnets and the Burgers hierarchy," *Journal of Statistical Physics*, vol. 183, no. 1, p. 12, 2021.
- [10] E. Agliari, F. Alemanno, A. Barra, M. Centonze, and **A. Fachechi**, "Neural networks with a redundant representation: Detecting the undetectable," *Physical review letters*, vol. 124, no. 2, p. 028 301, 2020.
- [11] E. Agliari, F. Alemanno, A. Barra, and **A. Fachechi**, "Generalized Guerra's interpolation schemes for dense associative neural networks," *Neural Networks*, vol. 128, pp. 254–267, 2020.
- [12] E. Agliari, F. Alemanno, A. Barra, *et al.*, "Analysis of temporal correlation in heart rate variability through maximum entropy principle in a minimal pairwise glassy model," *Scientific Reports*, vol. 10, no. 1, p. 15 353, 2020.
- [13] E. Agliari, A. Barra, O. A. Barra, **A. Fachechi**, L. Franceschi Vento, and L. Moretti, "Detecting cardiac pathologies via machine learning on heart-rate variability time series and related markers," *Scientific Reports*, vol. 10, no. 1, p. 8845, 2020.
- [14] E. Agliari, A. Fachechi, and C. Marullo, "The relativistic Hopfield model with correlated patterns," *Journal of Mathematical Physics*, vol. 61, no. 12, 2020.
- [15] F. Alemanno, M. Centonze, and A. Fachechi, "Interpolating between boolean and extremely high noisy patterns through minimal dense associative memories," *Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical*, vol. 53, no. 7, p. 074 001, 2020.
- [16] E. Agliari, F. Alemanno, A. Barra, and A. Fachechi, "Dreaming neural networks: Rigorous results," *Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment*, vol. 2019, no. 8, p. 083503, 2019.
- [17] E. Agliari, F. Alemanno, A. Barra, and **A. Fachechi**, "On the Marchenko–Pastur law in analog bipartite spin-glasses," *Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical*, vol. 52, no. 25, p. 254 002, 2019.
- [18] A. Fachechi, E. Agliari, and A. Barra, "Dreaming neural networks: Forgetting spurious memories and reinforcing pure ones," *Neural Networks*, vol. 112, pp. 24–40, 2019.
- [19] E. Alfinito, A. Barra, M. Beccaria, A. Fachechi, and G. Macorini, "An evolutionary game model for behavioral gambit of loyalists: Global awareness and risk-aversion," *Europhysics Letters*, vol. 121, no. 3, p. 38 001, 2018.
- [20] A. Barra, M. Beccaria, and **A. Fachechi**, "A new mechanical approach to handle generalized Hopfield neural networks," *Neural Networks*, vol. 106, pp. 205–222, 2018.
- [21] **A. Fachechi**, G. Macorini, and M. Beccaria, "Chiral trace relations in supersymmetric gauge theories," *Theoretical and Mathematical Physics*, vol. 196, no. 3, pp. 1282–1293, 2018.

- [22] E. Alfinito, M. Beccaria, **A. Fachechi**, and G. Macorini, "Reactive immunization on complex networks," *Europhysics Letters*, vol. 117, no. 1, p. 18 002, 2017.
- [23] M. Beccaria, A. Fachechi, and G. Macorini, "Chiral trace relations in  $\Omega$ -deformed  $\mathcal{N}=2$  theories," *Journal of High Energy Physics*, vol. 2017, no. 5, pp. 1–37, 2017.
- [24] M. Beccaria, A. Fachechi, and G. Macorini, "On the cusp anomalous dimension in the ladder limit of  $\mathcal{N}=4$  sym," *Journal of High Energy Physics*, vol. 2016, no. 6, pp. 1–21, 2016.
- [25] M. Beccaria, **A. Fachechi**, and G. Macorini, "Virasoro vacuum block at next-to-leading order in the heavy-light limit," *Journal of High Energy Physics*, vol. 2016, no. 2, pp. 1–22, 2016.
- [26] M. Beccaria, A. Fachechi, G. Macorini, and L. Martina, "Exact partition functions for  $\Omega$ -deformed  $\mathcal{N}=2$  theories with  $N_f=4$  flavours," *Journal of High Energy Physics*, vol. 2016, no. 12, pp. 1–41, 2016.

### **Conference Proceedings**

- [1] **A. Fachechi**, G. Macorini, and M. Beccaria, "Chiral trace relations in  $\Omega$ -deformed  $\mathcal{N}=2$  theories," in *Journal of Physics: Conference Series*, IOP Publishing, vol. 965, 2018, p. 012 013.
- [2] E. Alfinito, M. Beccaria, **A. Fachechi**, G. Macorini, *et al.*, "Probing complexity with epidemics: A new reactive immunization strategy.," in *COMPLEXIS*, 2017, pp. 116–123.

#### Selected talks to conferences and invited talks

- A Hopfield-like picture to address generalization and overfitting, Mathematics for Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning, University Bocconi of Milano.
- Dreaming Neural Networks: pushing retrieval/learning capabilities to the limit by "sleeping" mechanism, Physics-informed machine learning workshop, Alan Turing Institute.
  - Machine Learning from a spin-glass theory perspective, Stochastic Models for Complex Systems, Department of Mathematics E. De Giorgi, Unisalento.
  - Retrieving, unlearning and learning: there and back again, Department of Physics, Sapienza University of Rome.
- Dreaming Neural Networks: pushing retrieval/learning capabilities to the limit by "sleeping" mechanism, Matematica per l'Intelligenza Artificiale e il Machine Learning Giovani ricercatori, Politecnico di Torino.
  - PDE/Statistical Mechanics relation: from p-spin ferromagnets to dense associative memories, Department of Mathematics, Sapienza University of Rome.
  - Dreaming Neural Networks: pushing retrieval/learning capabilities to the limit by "sleeping" mechanism, Unconventional Computation Workshop, Swansea University.
- Dreaming Neural Networks: dal richiamo automatico all'apprendimento, Divulgazioni Notturne di Fisica Matematica, online talk for GNFM (Gruppo Nazionale della Fisica Matematica).
- Sleeping in Hopfield neural networks: some recent results, Department of Mathematics, King's College London.
- Chiral trace relations in  $\Omega$ -deformed  $\mathcal{N}=2$  theories, XXVth International Conference on Integrable Systems and Quantum symmetries, Czech Technical University Prague.
  - Chiral trace relations in  $\Omega$ -deformed  $\mathcal{N}=2$  theories, Physics and Mathematics of Nonlinear Phenomena "50 years of IST", Unisalento.